Guide to the Voices of Brooklyn oral histories 2008.031
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Voices of Brooklyn oral histories: Community activists, 2007-; 2008.031.4
  - Holtz, Joe, 2008 September 5; 2008.031.4.002
    Joe Holtz is a founding member, served on the Board of Directors, and remains a General Coordinator of the Park Slope Food Coop, a food cooperative market in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn. Holtz became an adult in the late 1960s, when multiple social causes were trending mainstream. Awareness of food science also grew in the early 1970s, and that period overlapped with Holtz's arrival in New York City. He settled in Park Slope as a renter and later as a homeowner. With other founders in place, the Coop opened in February of 1973 and management began tinkering with how to make the cooperative system of customers/owners/workers a viable, sustainable operation. The Coop was originally in a space that was sublet by a community center. In 1978, with over a thousand members, the Coop made a down payment to buy 782 Union Street. Two neighboring buildings were purchased in the two decades that followed. In 2016, membership was between 16,000 and 17,000.
    In this interview, Joe Holtz identifies the various strains of food cooperatives and how Park Slope Food Coop fits in with the members-only ownership and sales model. He recalls the founding principles of the Coop, and the other models of coops on the city marketplace in the early 1970s. He discusses the rollout of their labor strategy and the growing interest in food sources and research in that era. He speaks about the physical spaces the Coop has occupied, some organizing principles, and membership fluctuations. Holtz points out several ways the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn has benefitted from the Coop's practices. He also sees the pressures that gentrification is having on the area, in general and through firsthand examples. With the Coop a success, he has advised other newly-forming coops. In closing, Holtz speaks to the benefits and tensions of the rules for members working at the Coop, the approach to product boycotts, and how the Board of Directors functions. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Buildings, structures, etc.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Environmentalism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Food -- Social aspects; Food supply |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Markets |z New York (State) |z New York; New York (N.Y.); Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Social justice |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Park Slope Food Coop
  - Jackson, Esther Cooper, 2010 February 8; 2008.031.4.003
    Esther Cooper Jackson was born in in Arlington, Virginia in 1917. The younger of two children, her father was an officer in the Army and her mother was a bureaucrat who worked for the Forest Service, as well as an activist. Jackson graduated from Dunbar High School in Washington, D.C. She went to Oberlin College and then onto Fisk University, where she received a master's degree in sociology. Jackson moved to Birmingham, Alabama in 1940 to work on a voter registration project; spending seven years working there as a community organizer. She met her husband during that era, and they later decided to move to New York City in the early 1950s. Settling in Brooklyn, Jackson began working as an activist and board member with the Committee to Defend Negro Leadership. In 1961, she became a founding member and managing editor of the magazine Freedomways. She continued at the magazine for a quarter century. Jackson followed that with work as an activist and speaker, all while living in the same apartment in the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn since 1963. As recently as 2015, she had donated many personal papers to the New York University library.
    In the interview, Esther Cooper Jackson begins by describing the lives of her mother and father. Among many of her own biographical details, she talks about her early life in Arlington, Virginia and her education. She notes her thesis at Fisk University has been re-discovered by a number of contemporary academics. Jackson discusses the seven years she spent working as a community organizer in Birmingham, Alabama. She gives a basic picture of the civil inequalities African-Americans faced in the South. Jackson recalls her move to Brooklyn and her involvement in Freedomways magazine, a Black quarterly dedicated to art and culture. Throughout, she shares details and anecdotes about her daughters. The interview ends with her reflections on the change in the racial makeup of the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn in the late 2000s. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
    African Americans |x Civil rights |x History |y 20th century; African Americans -- Civil rights -- New York (State) -- New York; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Brownsville (New York, N.Y.); Community organizing |z New York (State) |z New York; Editors |z New York (State) |z New York; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (N.Y.); Segregation |z United States |x History; Social justice |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Southern States |x History; Virginia; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation
  - Pearsall, Nancy, 2007 February 15 and 21; 2008.031.4.004
  - Wolfe, Maxine, 2008 September 2; 2008.031.4.006
    Maxine Wolfe was born in 1941 and raised in a working-class, Jewish family in Brooklyn. Attending public school, she graduated from New Utrecht High School at age sixteen. Wolfe went on to Brooklyn College, receiving an undergraduate degree in psychology. She attained her doctoral degree in social psychology from the City University of New York (CUNY). Later, Wolfe was a professor in that school's Environmental Psychology Program. Having had an interest in activism since her teens, Wolfe joined and supported several organizations, being a notable mentor in ACT UP beginning in 1987. In 1984, while living in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn, Wolfe began attending weekly volunteer meetings of the Lesbian Herstory Archives (LHA). With the collections growing, LHA fundraised and coordinated the purchase of a house in Park Slope in 1990. The Archives were moved there from the Upper West Side apartment of founder Joan Nestle in 1993. As of 2017, Wolfe remains a coordinator at LHA and a professor emeritus at CUNY's Graduate Center.
    In the interview, Maxine Wolfe describes the Lesbian Herstory Archives (LHA) in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn. She lists the variety of collected genre types and, much later, the arrangement of the material; filling in with broad overviews and some specific details about the intellectual content of LHA. She recalls joining as a volunteer, and the event of moving the collection to a Park Slope house. Wolfe shares some history of LHA itself and some insight into its administration in the 2000s. She considers the community interaction of LHA and Park Slope, as well as the effects of gentrification, activism and homogenization in the area. Returning to the internal activity of the Archives, Wolfe gives an overview of the visiting researchers and guests, the collection policy, staffing, and decision-making. In conclusion, she emphasizes the open access principles of LHA. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
    Activism; Activists -- New York (State) -- New York; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; History |x Research |z North America; Lesbians; Libraries |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Social justice |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Social movements |z United States; Women |z United States |x Social conditions
- Voices of Brooklyn oral histories: Our neighbors, 2007-; 2008.031.5
  This series includes oral histories collected through several projects undertaken by the Brooklyn Historical Society beginning in 2007. The assembled collection took shape in 2008 under the project title "Brooklyn History Makers." The ongoing oral history collection, retitled in 2016, features a diverse range of narrators; all longtime neighborhood residents who describe the changes they have observed in their neighborhoods over decades.
  - Abumrad, Jad and Karla Murthy, 2010 August 29; 2008.031.5.001
  - Castellano, Madeline, 2009 May 12; 2008.031.5.002
    Madeline Rotondo Castellano was born in Brooklyn in 1927. She was raised in the Fort Greene, Canarsie, and Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhoods of Brooklyn. Later, she resided in the Flatbush neighborhood of Brooklyn. In her earliest years, she lived in a home that included three generations of her Italian American family. Castellano's childhood was spent running chores for family, seeing friends in Fort Greene Park, and attending school. While still a young girl, she was permanently injured in a hit-and-run incident. It left her without the full use of her legs. Castellano was one of seven siblings. She married, raised a daughter, and later divorced. After working in jobs at movie theaters and a shop, she became an advocate for improved social services for the physically challenged. In her late fifties, she returned to school at Adelphi University and held a long-term bookkeeping position with Citibank. As of 2009, she was residing at an assisted living facility in the Coney Island neighborhood of Brooklyn.
    In the interview, Madeline Rontondo Castellano shares anecdotes that reflect her way of life in the Brooklyn of the Great Depression, Second World War, and postwar eras. She also formulates that society's issues of the 2000s grew out of those earlier periods. The three-generation family unit in which she grew up in the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn is illustrated in vignettes about her running errands, taking part in Sunday dinners, and entertaining visiting neighbors. Castellano also discusses her times of taking responsibility for herself as a little girl and teenager, with Fort Greene Park, area social clubs, and the Brooklyn Navy Yard as backdrops. She recalls her family history and Italian heritage. In several segments throughout the interview, Castellano relates the story of her injury by hit-and-run driver at age nine, being hospitalized, then treated differently in school, and later in life becoming an advocate for those with physical disabilities. In the final half-hour, Castellano looks at her adult life as a mother and wife, and how she ended her marriage on her terms. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
    Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Fort Greene Park (New York, N.Y.); Games |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Great Depression |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; People with disabilities |x Services for |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945 |z New York (State) |z Kings County
  - Favorito, Vincent, 2011 June 10; 2008.031.5.005
    Vincent Favorito was born in Brooklyn in 1941. He is of Italian heritage and he grew up in the Carroll Gardens neighborhood of Brooklyn. He attended school at Sacred Hearts-St. Stephen's (Hicks Street), Delehanty High School and later St. John's University and St. John's School of Law. At the time of this interview, Favorito and his wife had sold the Carroll Gardens brownstone that his father-in-law bought in 1946 and where he and his wife first lived in 1962 when they got married. They returned to live in the brownstone in 2003 after his father-in-law passed away. From 1972 – 2003, they lived in the Marine Park neighborhood of Brooklyn and that is where their three children grew up. Favorito and his wife, having sold their brownstone shortly before this 2011 interview, planned to move to Westchester to be closer to one of their sons and live in a condominium without too many stairs.
    In this interview, Vincent Favorito remembers his childhood in the Carroll Gardens neighborhood of Brooklyn and the schools he attended through to his adulthood. He recalls the Italian families in the neighborhood and the bakeries, butchers, and other neighborhood businesses. He talks about adult life in different homes in Carroll Gardens and the Marine Park neighborhood of Brooklyn, with summers on Breezy Point in Queens. Favorito discusses being part of the 1969 effort to get landmark status for Carroll Gardens. He reflects on the importance of "the Place blocks" (First – Fourth Places) built in 1846. He also relates how the construction of the Brooklyn-Queens Expressway divided the neighborhood and destroyed the commerce along Union Street. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
    Architecture |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x History |y 19th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History; Brooklyn-Queens Expressway (New York, N.Y.); Brownstone buildings |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Carroll Gardens (New York, N.Y.); City planning |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Clinton Street (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Historic preservation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Home ownership |x Social aspects |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County
  - Garcia, Yolande, 2010 September 29; 2008.031.5.006
    Yolande Garcia was born and raised in Haiti in 1930, moving to New York City in 1954 to start a new life. She met her husband in the city and had two children, a boy and a girl, while living in Queens. In 1980, they moved to the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn where they have lived ever since. Highly involved in community activism and global humanitarian work, Garcia had spent thirty years in Fort Greene, helping to improve the neighborhood, and enjoying her retirement with her husband, children, and grandchildren. She visited Haiti every year and has deep roots to the community in both her home country and her adopted country. Garcia's son, Marc, was also interviewed for this collection.
    In this interview, Yolande Garcia discusses immigrating to New York City and moving to the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn later in life. She talks about her role in starting a block association, creating a safe neighborhood, and the changes she has witnessed in Fort Greene throughout the past three decades. She reflects on her family roots in Haiti, her activism in Haiti and in Fort Greene, and on raising a family in the city. She describes her love of music and the arts and the different venues she frequents around Brooklyn. She talks about the benefits she sees in living in a multicultural neighborhood, the sensory experiences of Fort Greene, and her love of the neighborhood she adopted as her own. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Fort Greene Park (New York, N.Y.); Haiti; Haitian Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Intergenerational relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Neighborhoods -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Women in charitable work |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Garcia, Yolande
  - Glicksman, Hal, 2009 January 14; 2008.031.5.007
    Born in Brooklyn in 1937, Hal Glicksman grew up in the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn at the same location as his father's glass shop. He attended PS 11, PS 64, Boys' High School, and Brooklyn College. While young Glicksman was in his teens his father suffered a heart attack, and the young man assisted with glass installation for the family business. Permanently shuttering the shop in the early 1970s, Glicksman left for Chicago, where he got started in local broadcast television work. He returned to Brooklyn a couple years later and found long term employment with CBS News. In the several years before this 2009 interview, Glicksman had become a Manhattan resident, left CBS after staffing cuts, and had become a tour guide in the city for the Gray Line bus company. After eight years at Gray Line, he was leading a variety of tours for New York City Vacation Packages as of 2017.
    In this interview, Hal Glicksman looks back on his time as a boy and young man in and around the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn, as well as shares the knowledge of a tour guide in regard to the Brooklyn of the early twenty-first century. Throughout, he mentions many biographical details and recalls much about the two generations of his family that preceded him. Glicksman recalls his home and how that also served as the base for his father's glass shop. He focuses on notable moments and landmarks of the Brooklyn Dodgers, and shares personal stories of volunteering for the team and meeting Dan Bankhead and Jackie Robinson. Often Glicksman discusses the changes in Brooklyn neighborhoods, contrasting a location of his youth with his adult view of the same place. The landmarks and institutions mentioned include Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church, Fort Greene Park, elevated trains, Ebbets Field, Barclay's Center, Brooklyn Navy Yard, Pfizer Pharmaceutical, Fort Greene Meat Market, and Brooklyn Academy of Music. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
    Baseball |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Baseball fields |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Clinton Hill (New York, N.Y.); Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Games |x Street |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Jews, American |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; School children--New York (State)--Kings County; Tourism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bankhead, Dan; Boys' High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Academy of Music; Brooklyn Dodgers (Baseball team); Ebbets Field (New York, N.Y.); Glicksman, Hal; New York Naval Shipyard
  - Holland, Deborah "DK", 2010 March 1; 2008.031.5.010
    Born in 1947, Deborah "DK" Holland was a Manhattan resident until 1983. She was teaching a graphic design class at Pratt Institute then, and was wooed to the Clinton Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn because of the value for housing stock at the time and the welcoming sense of community within the social gatherings of the Society for Clinton Hill. She renovated the home she bought there, but soon found it too large for a single person. She relocated to a home that had been a tack barn on Adelphi Street at Lafayette Avenue. The property also included a corner storefront that, in 2017, housed the restaurant Olea. Holland built on the Society's community values and, in 1984, started a newsletter with neighbors titled The Hill, the Journal of Fort Greene, Clinton Hill and Wallabout. It had also become a website by 2010, but ceased publication that same year. Holland co-founded the Greene Hill Food Co-op, a long gestating organization that opened its doors in 2011. In 2017, she had co-founded the education-focused non-profit Inquiring Minds. More of her biographical details can be found at dkholland.com
    In this interview, "DK" Holland focuses mainly on her life in the Clinton Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn. She chronicles her experiences with homes there; her neighbors' as well as her own. Holland discusses her involvement with the Board of the Society for Clinton Hill, and the efforts between her, Abigail Golde, and Rogen Brown in getting a newsletter into circulation for Clinton Hill, and the nearby Fort Greene and Wallabout neighborhoods of Brooklyn. Holland surveys the changes in her area; from a crime-ridden era to more recent times when fine dining and a food co-op are becoming staples. In her eyes, it's neighborliness and home restoration that have strengthened the community. Other tools that Holland emphasizes are organizing sustainably and patronizing businesses. Interview conducted by Alexis Taines Coe.
    Architecture |x Conservation and restoration; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Clinton Hill (New York, N.Y.); Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Markets |z New York (State) |z New York; Neighborhoods -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Wallabout (New York, N.Y.); Women in community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brown, Rogen S.; Golde, Abigail; Greene Hill Food Coop (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Hill (Newsletter); Olea (Restaurant); Society for Clinton Hill
  - Moran, Ed, 2008 November 12; 2008.031.5.016
    Edward "Ed" Moran was born in 1947 and raised in a small town of Pennsylvania. At age twenty in 1968, he sailed to Europe for a four-month tour of the continent. Moving to New York City later that year, he lived in Manhattan until 1974. After moving to Brooklyn, he joined a theatrical company that performed at Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church. In 1976, he formally became a member of the church. He became an Elder with the Session of the church a year later and after less involvement in the church for much of the 1980s, he joined the Session again from 1989 to 1991. Writing for a living, Moran is recognized as the unofficial historian of Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church; knowledgeable about the church's mid-nineteenth century origin and subsequent decades, and equipped with first-hand observations of the 1970s through the 2000s.
    In this first of three interviews, Edward "Ed" Moran begins with his initial contact with the Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church and Reverend George Knight due to his interest in the theatre group that performed there. He looks at the special nature of the church services in that they didn't conform to type. Moran reflects on his own journey in the tumultuous late-1960s that led him to New York City, then Brooklyn, and his rapid rise in the church's hierarchy. He speaks to the social justice mission of the church, its use of history for perspective and learning, and its forward-thinking legacy. Moran spends much of the middle of the interview dissecting whether the church played a role in abolition or the Underground Railroad in Brooklyn. He shares a few short anecdotes of some of the most memorable congregants and occasions. Moran then looks back at the 1970s and 1980s when the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn was struggling and the church was actively reaching out to the community. In closing, he considers Reverend Knight's attachment to the church and that it may have been pathological. Interview conducted by Hillel Arnold.